בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *Daf* is דף ק' *Daf Kuf*,
100, and we pick up on the bottom of צ"ט עמוד ב'
*Tzadi Tes Amud Bais*, אמר רבא Amar Rava, *Amar Rava*. And my
thoughts are with our friend Joe and his wife Goldie, that this
learning should be in her merit.
And we pick up with אמר רבא Rava. *Amar Rava* two lines
from the bottom, and we're dealing now with specific interesting scenarios relating
to carrying. So we talked about like throwing dirt into a well,
taking dirt out of a well, and in that act making it
into a רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid, *Reshus Hayachid* or or changing it
from a רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid. *Reshus Hayachid*. So we continue with
interesting types of scenarios right now. אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava*, so
said רבא Rava. *Rava*. פשיטא לי *Peshita li*, it's obvious to me
that מים אגבי מים *Mayim agabi mayim*, we had this before, water
floating on water, היינו הנחתן *Hainu hanachasan*, that's like their location. So
if you have a you know, some like pond of water or
well of water, and you scooped water off of the top layer,
and you you know, and you carried it from a let's say
a private domain to a public domain, you've carried. You've removed it
from the place in which it is מונח munach *Munach*, you know,
set. Something has to be taken from a set location and put
down in a set way. It's not be like flying through air
and all those issues we just discussed. So that's going to be
a lot of focus today is exactly what's considered to be מונח
munach... *Munach*, that the thing is either placed down or removed from
a from being in a set place. So רבא Rava *Rava* says
water on water, that's obvious, that's all like you know, it's all
seen as that is the place for water. That's a set place.
The contrast will make this more obvious. אגוז אגבי מים *Egoz agabi
mayim*, however if you have a nut floating on water, לאו היינו
הנחתן *Lav hainu hanachasan*. That's not there considered that it is מונח
munach. *Munach*. So if let's say you carry a nut into a
רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim, *Reshus harabbim* and you you put it down
on a pond or you remove a nut from a pond and
you carry it you know from one domain to the next or
four אמות amot *Amos*, you have not done either an עקירה *Akira*
or an הנחה hanacha, *Hanacha*. You have not done an הנחה hanacha.
*Hanacha*, you have not placed it down in a fixed way because
it's not on solid ground, it's moving around. You have not removed
it from a fixed location. So interestingly although we've talked about ideas
which are much more radical than this, like passing through the airspace
of a רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim, *Reshus harabbim*, קלוטה כמאן שהונחה דמיא
*Kluta keman shehunacha damya*, passing through the airspace of a house, ביתא
כמאן דמליא דמי *Beisa keman demalya dami*, you know things just in
the middle of the air or a you know a like a
a date, a clump of dates stuck to a wall. All those
things are considered מונח munach, *Munach*, but somehow floating on water is
not. Again the question, you know, there is a question whether everybody
always agrees with all those other positions that have been stated, but
it somehow it seems that the basic fact that water moves, you
know although if it's stuck to a wall eventually it'll fall, it'll
the stickiness'll fall off, but at least for this moment it's considered
stable. Something on water is not considered stable.
Is it like a plane, that something on a plane, because the
airplane is floating moving, right.
But it's moving, you're not moving.
So that's an excellent question.
So that's essentially the next question in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Let's
take a look.
So let's say I take a a boat and I put it
in the water.
That is that is הנחה hanacha. *Hanacha*. No, because it's still not
it's not it's not just that it's not its normal location is
that it's moving.
Water's not considered moving, water on water is that's all just water.
So the water is in the pond. The water is not on
the water. But anything else on the water, even if you've got
your little toy boat or real boat in the water, so it's
not because it's not considered that it's natural for it to be
there, it might be natural, but because it's on water it's it's
not considered stable, it's not considered fixed. Okay let's take a look
at the next example. בעי רבא Rava *Boei Rava*, so רבא Rava,
*Rava* asked, אגוז בכלי וכלי צף אגבי מים מהו *Egoz bikli v'kli
tzaf agabi mayim mahu*? And this is essentially I think like Rivka's
question about the plane or the train. About relative location. You put
your your nut on a in a vessel like in let's say
a dish and the dish is floating on the water. What's the
story? So or like you put something on a boat and the
boat is on the water, you put something on a train and
the train is moving. מי אמרינן בתר אגוז אזלינן *Mi amrinan basar
egoz azlinan*? Do we look relative to the object you placed down,
so relative to the nut? והניח *V'hanyach*. So the nut's location is
not the water, the nut's location is the the dish or the
nut's location is the boat or the train and it's stable vis-a-vis
the dish, vis-a-vis the train, vis-a-vis the boat. And therefore you have
put it in a stable location. או דלמא בתר כלי kli? אזלינן
*Odilma basar kli azlinan*? Or do we say no, because the very
thing it's on, the vessel, is itself moving? והלא נייח *V'halo nayach*.
And it's not and that is not at rest. תיקו teku. *Teiku*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that we don't know, so that
remains an unanswered question. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks this type
of thing not just by שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*, but in other scenarios
as well, you know whether you look at something's location relative to
the immediate thing it's in or and or whether you look at
it sort of in terms of the bigger picture. So
here you see also, it's not just the question of like, is
it natural or not natural and so on, but is it considered
to be in a fixed location and even that is fixed relative
to what? I mean anything on the earth is fixed relative I
don't know to the sun. Yes, Charlie.
The water under water so that would seem to apply by that
logic to any liquid you pour into a...
Ah, so we're about to talk about that about two separate types
of liquids that have different...
densities. Second question, it would seem that that would have some, the
second issue would have some applicability to can you be on a
boat that is traveling on שבת? Shabbos.
Well we're going to get to that actually when we turn the
next page but... but here actually that, you know, is this just
adds greater leniency that anything put down on might not be considered
like fixed location. Now of course the boat issue, you know, raises
a question like a vessel is still like manipulated by me. So
if it's a nut in a vessel you could still say look
at it relative to the, you know, look at it relative to
the dish, you know, but if you're on a boat that's I
don't know, ten city blocks long, you know, whatever, it's the size
of a, of a town, you know, which are some of these
boats, would you really say oh you have to look at it
relative to the water? You know, at a certain stage obviously that
thing defines your sort of, you know, your environment, not the water
that it's on. But in this case it's a more interesting question
because it's, you know, because you can manipulate both the nut and
the dish and but so do you look at the nut relative
to the dish or the whole thing relative to let's say the
pond? So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו. Now, שמן על גבי יין,
shemen al gabei yayin, this is sort of Charlie's question. I didn't
read ahead. Okay yeah no you have oil on a wine or
oil on water you could say.
Both... so the oil will... will float because the oil is less
dense. So what's the story? Is that considered to be, is that
like a nut on the water or is the oil and the
wine all considered to be one unit like water on water? So
that the גמרא Gemara says מחלוקת רבי יוחנן בן נורי ורבנן. machlokes
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri ve-Rabbanan. That seems to be... the... a debate
רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri and the Rabbis at
another location applied here. What's that debate? תנן, tnan, we taught in
the משנה. Mishnah. שמן שצף על גבי יין, shemen she-tzaf al gabei
yayin, you have oil floating on wine. נטמא טבול יום בשמן, nitma
t'vul yom ba-shemen, now both of them are תרומה. terumah. תרומה terumah
can become טמא tamei by a שני, sheni, it can be a
שלישי shelishi but it can't go any further. Now a טבול יום,
t'vul yom, somebody that went to the מקוה mikvah that day for
whatever טומאה tumah and is waiting for nightfall to be 100 percent
טהור, tahor, his status is equivalent to that of a שני. sheni.
If he touches תרומה terumah he makes it טמא. tamei. The תרומה
terumah though, now that it became טמא tamei through a שני sheni
is a שלישי shelishi or it's called פסול, pasul, it can't make
anything else טמא. tamei. So if you have here, you have your
wine let's say and... let me do it this way so I
don't ruin my coffee... and you got
your oil on top of your wine, if it's seen as one
unit then I touch this, I've touched the whole unit, I've made
it all טמא, tamei, it's all תרומה. terumah. But if it's seen
as separate I've only made the oil טמא, tamei, the oil is
touching the wine, that does not make the wine טמא, tamei, so
can I now drink the wine is the question. Is the wine
תרומה טמאה? terumah tmei'ah? So what's the הלכה? halacha? לא פסול אלא
שמן, lo pasul ela shemen, you only invalidated the oil, that's what
the Rabbis say. The oil and the wine are separate. רבי יוחנן
בן נורי אומר שניהם חיבור זה לזה. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri omer
shneihem chibbur zeh l'zeh. It's all liquid so even though there are
layers to it it's all considered one big unit and therefore you
touch the whole thing. So according to רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri if you put oil on wine or removed oil
from wine it's all one unit, it's like water and water and
you actually have removed it from a fixed location. But according to
the Rabbis nope, if you put the oil on the wine you've
placed it on, they're separate, it's like the nut on the wine
or the nut on water and therefore it is not fixed and
you are exempt. Okay now that whole thing was very interesting but
again it really the biggest חידוש chidush I would say more than
the interesting questions of oil and wine and nut in a dish
on water was the sort of assumption that that whole discussion made.
The assumption that something is not considered מונח if it's a little
bit moving around. Again given that we've had opinions about, you know,
something thrown through רשות הרבים, reshus harabim thrown through רשות היחיד, reshus
ha-yachid. all those things are מונח... at least to some opinions are
considered מונח. You would have said okay even if I'm not going
to go that far it has to be on the ground, but
if it's a little bit moving around, the assumption that being on
water is not מונח, that was that assumption was I think a
bit certainly a big חידוש chidush even before you got to the
interesting subcases of that. Now we have אביי Abaye who goes back
to some of the issues or related discussion of some of the
issues we saw yesterday. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, said אביי. Abaye. בור
ברשות הרבים עמוקה עשרה ורחבה שמונה. bor bi-reshus ha-rabim amukah asarah ve-rechevah
shmonah. You have a pit in רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, it's ten
deep and it's eight wide, so it's, you know, twice as big
as it needs to be in terms of the width to be
a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. It is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid,
וזרק לתוכה מחצלת, ve-zarak l'tochah machtzeles, you threw a mat into it,
חייב, chayav, and the mat just landed, so you're חייב, chayav, fine,
that's obvious, that's really a setup for the next point. חלקה במחצלת
chilkah be-machtzeles פטור. patur.
Let's say you divided it with a mat, then you're פטור. patur.
So if basically... let's use this as the example right? So if
you have here this big back here.
Okay here you have here this is the big... The base of
your pit, it's got the walls ten, the base is eight. Okay,
let's say it's eight by four, alright? But it's double the width
that you need for a שיעור של יחיד. shiur shel yachid. And
then you threw into it a mat, and the mat landed like
that, smack down, it was a perfect throw, okay? Maybe you placed
it in, okay? Now, now you have two, two things here which
are like walls around them, neither of which is רשות היחיד. reshus
hayachid. Why not? Because there's the thickness of the mat. So the
space here is less than ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim and the space
here is less than ארבעה טפחים. arba tefachim. So by throwing the
mat in, it stops being, now neither half of this well is
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid. but when you started it was. Very
similar to the discussion we had yesterday when you threw dirt in
and it made it lower the height, here you're throwing a wall
in and it's lowering the width. But either way, after you're done,
it stops being a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid, What is the story?
Do we look at it before you started or after you finished?
Wait, it could have also made it less because it was ten
and now the thickness of the mat?
That's what I was thinking. Alright, so that is,
well, I'll get to that in a minute, but let's assume at
least in the first case it's not exactly ten, but I will
relate to your case in a minute. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so
חלקה במחצלת, chelka bemachatzeles, so he says that you're פטור patur because
when you finish, it stops being a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid, So
גמרא Gemara. says, לאביי דפשיטא ליה דמחצלת מבטלה מחיצה, leAbaye depishita lei
demachatzeles mevatla mechitza,
according to אביי Abaye it's obvious that even a mat sort of,
you know, redefines the architecture, and since at the end it's not
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, you're פטור. patur. כל שכן חויא דמבטלה
מחיצה, kol shekein chuya demavatla mechitza, he would certainly agree that if
you did, if you threw in dirt, which was the other case
yesterday, רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's case, that certainly redefines the architecture, that's
a more permanent change. So if you threw in dirt and made
it less than עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, right, you'd be פטור, patur,
that's a more permanent change. It's obvious if a mat is considered
to change the architecture, certainly dirt would. לרבי יוחנן דמיבעיא ליה חויא,
leRabbi Yochanan demibaia lei chuya, according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan he
wasn't sure if even dirt maybe makes you פטור, patur, even when
that really is a serious change of the architecture, so מחצלת פשיטא
דלא מבטלה מחיצה, machatzeles pishita dela mavatla mechitza, he would actually say
in אביי's Abaye's case you'd be חייב. chayav. Why? There's two questions
here, right? One question is do you go by the configuration before
the act is finished or do you look at it after the
act is finished? Before the act is finished it's a רשות היחיד,
reshus hayachid, after it's finished it's not. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and אביי Abaye say, or אביי Abaye says no, you look at
it after it's finished. After it's finished it's not a רשות היחיד,
reshus hayachid, you get off, fine. But there's another question. The other
question is even if you look at it after it's finished, how
much, you know, if you have, what type of an object redefines
the architecture? Remember we spoke about like the wad of dates stuck
to the wall? That doesn't redefine the architecture, that's seen as only
temporary. What type of object redefines the architecture? So the גמרא Gemara
is saying a mat much less so than dirt. Dirt filling up
a hole much more redefines the architecture than a mat. So אביי
Abaye who said a mat you're פטור patur means two things: A,
you look at it after it's done, after it's done it's not
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, and B, even a mat is enough
to redefine the architecture. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan didn't know what the
story was with dirt, even though it was, you know, he didn't
know whether you go before or after, but he was talking about
dirt which really makes a significant change. So גמרא Gemara. says according
to him, it would be obvious that a mat, which is much
less of a change of the configuration, that clearly you would actually
be חייב, chayav, it would not redefine the architecture, you would still
look at it as a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, and therefore you
would be חייב. chayav. Okay, so אביי Abaye and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan to some degree are asking the same question: do you look
at it before or after? But there's also another factor is what
is the object being put in, does it redefine or not? אביי
Abaye thinks a mat can redefine, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says at
most we're talking about dirt, okay, mat certainly not, and therefore you'd
be חייב chayav in the case of a mat. Now, how about,
you know, Michael's point which is the point about like how many,
what type of object do we think would redefine, like how far
would, you know, how far might it go according to אביי Abaye
that says a mat? So תוספות Tosafot here says, let me just
find the right תוספות, Tosafot,
no, he's going to do it on the next גמרא. Gemara So
let's wait until we read the next גמרא Gemara and then we'll
get back to Michael's question. ואמר אביי, Ve'amar Abaye, and אביי Abaye
said, בור ברשות הרבים עמוק עשרה ורחב ארבעה, bor bereshus harabim amok
asara verachav arba'a, you have your classic pit in רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim, that's ten by four, so it's a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid
מלא מים, malei mayim, but let's say it's filled with water, or
half filled with water, doesn't matter, okay, whatever it is, וזרק לתוכה,
vezarak letocha, you throw something in it, חייב, chayav, you're חייב. chayav.
Because now we have a question: if dirt filling up a pit
stops it from being, or even partly filling up a pit stops
it from being a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid. so dirt redefines the
architecture, אביי Abaye said I just told you a mat redefines the
architecture, so how about if the pit is filled with water? Why
don't we say if the pit is half filled with water, from
the top of the water level to the top of the pit
is not עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, so you don't have, you don't
have רשות היחיד reshut hayachid, anymore. So no, somehow water, because I
guess it's normally in a pit and it's normally removed from a
pit, it's normally seen that the pit contains the water and it's
there to be put in and removed, then it does not define
the basic architecture configuration, it's still רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid You throw
something in even if it floats on the water, or I guess
no, floating on the water no because of what we said before.
So רש״י Rashi says you throw a rock in and it sinks
down, okay, but you still would be חייב. chayav. Now or let's
say you had a case, you had I don't know, you put
a nut in a dish and the dish on the water, let's
say according to what we said before that would be considered to
be, or you put water in, and water on water is coming
to a rest. Even if the object you put in is not
on the ground of it, it doesn't matter, it's in a רשות
היחיד, reshut hayachid. it's between the walls, and if the walls are
עשרה טפחים asara tefachim high, it's come to rest, let's say it
was water on water, you'd be חייב. chayav. It doesn't have to
be on the ground of a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid? as long
as you have actually עשרה טפחים asara tefachim walls. So what אביי
Abaye is saying is the water doesn't matter, it's still, you still
look at it as walls of that height. Now that's contrasted to
the following case: ומלאה פירות, umle'ah peirot, if it's filled with fruit,
okay, וזרק לתוכה פטור, vezarak letochah patur, you're exempt.
מאי טעמא mai ta'ama why? מים לא מבטלי מחיצה, mayim lo mevatlei
mechitza, the water does not negate the
walls, פירות מבטלי מחיצה peirot mevatlei mechitza negates the walls. תניא נמי
הכי, tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly: הזורק מן הים לאיסטריא, hazorek
min hayam le'istrya, if you throw from the ocean to a איסטריא.
istrya. איסטריא istrya is like stratia, like a road, a major road,
רשות הרבים, reshut harabim
או מן האיסטריא
לים, o min ha'istrya layam, or from this road to the ocean,
פטור, patur, you're exempt because an ocean is a כרמלית, karmelit, okay?
Doesn't have walls, isn't a רשות הרבים, reshut harabim. it's a כרמלית.
karmelit. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, Rabbi Shimon says: אם יש
במקום שזרק, im yesh bemakom shezarak, if in the place you threw
into the ocean there is in the floor עומק עשרה ורוחב ארבעה,
omek asara verochav arba'ah, a well 10 by 4, חייב, chayav, you're
liable. So imagine you've got the ocean floor and in the ocean
floor there's a little, I don't know, a little well as it
were, a little ditch dug into the ocean floor that's not level
with the ocean floor that's 10 by 4. Okay for somehow he
says you would look at that separate from the ocean floor and
you'd look at that as a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid? That's a
little strange because I mean why don't you just look at the
entire ocean floor as a רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid. Right I mean
because then if you've got, we'll discuss this in a minute, a
coral reef or a, what's the other thing called, it's not a
coral reef, anyway another type of, you know, the normal type of
an ocean thing, it's very gradual, it doesn't have wall-like edges, but
a coral reef, right?
And the continental shelf, shelf,
continental shelf, slope, the continental slope is very steep.
Okay so by the time you get, right, by the time you
get to the continental shelf, why don't you say the whole ocean
is רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid? So, you know, that's an interesting question,
but somehow we're bracketing that and we're saying for some reason we're
not going to look at that, but he is willing to look
at a little hole in the bottom of the ocean floor, maybe
we're not literally talking about ocean, maybe a river or whatever, as
a separate unit and that if it has 10 by 4, that's
a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid What's interesting for us though, why it's
relevant for us is the fact that even though it's filled with
water. So you see this idea that even though it's filled with
water it doesn't stop it from its identity. Now that is actually
even more surprising even again ignoring the other questions we raised because
that's filled with water in a way that it's never going to
be emptied from the water, right? I mean it's filled with water
because it's on the base of a river or of an ocean
or whatever. And somehow maybe why is it because water is transparent?
I mean it's, it's not even the idea that I was saying
before that it's, you know, it naturally is filled with it and
is removed from it, or maybe just somehow we think that wells
and water, water is always seen as, as being, as
the well contains the water, but you always identify it independent from
it. Anyway, that's a little strange that we're not even talking about
water that has to be removed. The fruit issue though raises other
question. Why not say the same about a fruit? I don't get
it. If I go ahead and I store fruit in a hole,
don't you, the fruit doesn't change the architecture of the hole, it's
just being stored there, I'm going to remove it, right? Let's say
I've got, you know, let's say I've got, let's say I've got
a, I don't know, some type of a, of a house and
I go and I fill it with, you know, with,
with, with like a granary and I fill it with grain. Does
it stop being a רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid. It's just contained within
it, the walls are still the walls. So תוספות Tosafot asks this
question. If you took a, take a look at תוספות Tosafot and
this is similar also to Micah's issue, question about the mat before.
פירות מבטלי מחיצה, peirot mevatlei mechitza, תוספות Tosafot says: ואם תאמר, ve'im
tomar, ומאי שנא מדבלה שמנה, umai shina midevela shemena, how's it different
than that sticky, you know, date thing, דאמרינן לעיל דלא מבטלי, de'amrinan
le'eil delo mevatlei, that we said before that it doesn't change the
configuration if you've got a date thing stuck on a wall? ואביי
דהכא אית ליה שינוי דבלה, va'Abaye de'hacha it lei shinui devela, and
Abaye holds of that, etc. ויש לומר, veyesh lomar, the middle of
the last wide line of תוספות, Tosafot, דדבלה
אינו עומד כל כך להתבטל שם בכותל, dedevela eino omed kol kach
lehitbatel sham bakotel, you're not going to leave the thing there against
the wall, כמו
שרגילין לבטל פירות בבור, kemo sheragilin levatel peirot babor, as you would
leave fruit in a pit, why would you leave it? כגון תבואה,
kegon tevu'ah, because he says we're not talking about apples. It's at
ושלמה, V'Shlomo, the middle of the last wide line of תוספות. Tosafot.
דדבלה אינו עומד כל כך להתבטל שם בכותל. De-dveilah eino omed kol
kach l'hitbatel sham b'kotel. You're not going to leave the thing there
against the wall כמו שרגילים לבטל פירות בבור. k'mo sheragilin levatel peirot
b'bor. You would leave fruit in a pit, right? כגון תבואה k'gon
tevuah because he says we're not talking about apples, we're talking about
grain. You know, so you put stuff in a granary, you keep
it there for like a half a year, you store your grain
there for a long period of time. Right? America has these grain
silos probably has its grain there for years, right? So if you
store it there for a long period of time, it is seen
as changing the basic configuration. It's now seen as not a thing
with walls and a what do you call
it, and a not a container, anyway, and some type of a
volume inside of it of a vacuum, you know, but it's actually
just seen as one solid unit. אי נמי Ina mi Tosafot says
דבלה דבר מועט הוא dveilah davar muat hu ולא מבטלה. v'lo m'vatlah.
Dveilah is a little thing relative to the whole structure. אבל בור
מלא פירות Aval bor malei peirot או חציו o chetzyo מבטל. mevatel.
He says maybe what we're talking about is not just a little
bit of fruit, maybe we're talking about it's filled with fruit or
the majority of it is filled and maybe that changes
the story. And then he asks like sort of Michael's point about
the math. והוא הדין דגרעין אחד V'hu hadin d'garin echad או דבר
מועט o davar muat לא מבטל lo mevatel ורשות היחיד. v'reshut hayachid.
Let's say you've got a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. here, right, you've
got your ten by four, and on the floor you have one
little grain of wheat. Okay, Tosafot says well why doesn't it stop
being ten טפחים tefachim high? Okay, or one little layer of grain
of wheat, right, or like Michael said you had your mats. Why
doesn't it stop? So obviously at a certain stage, obviously most things
we're saying they're contained in the רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid They don't
change the architecture of the רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Okay, so it's
only certain things. So what are the things? So Tosafot tries to
limit the case of fruit to either one or the other or
both of the following criteria. Number one, it's there for a long
period of time. You're not just putting it there and you're going
to take it out soon like a granary where you leave it
for a long period of time. And or two, that it is
filling half, all or at least half of the pit. And with
one or two of those criteria we can say that it changes
the configuration, but less not. Okay, so that's his basic answer to
that question. Again, the water at the bottom of the ocean is
still very bizarre. It fills it completely, it's there forever. Okay, so
why the water is not like that I don't know, but anyway
that's how Tosafot tries to limit this גמרא.
Gemara But you could say it's like apples, which you don't just
put in there, or you did put it in there and left
it in there for a long time which is...
Yeah, I don't know, that's a good question too. Is it your
subjective intent to leave it there for a long time? Is it
conventionally that it's there for a long time? All those are very
good questions. Okay, now we move on to the next משנה. Mishnah.
The volume is gonna change. If you put a fruit in it's
gonna lose moisture, it's gonna go down.
Well that's true also. Okay, so now the משנה Mishnah says like
this, הזורק ארבע אמות בכותל, Hazorek arba amot b'kotel, this is something
that we've quoted many times, הזורק ארבע אמות בכותל, hazorek arba amot
b'kotel, you threw something four אמות amot in a רשות הרבים reshut
harabim, and it hit a wall. למעלה מעשרה טפחים, Lemalah m'asarah tefachim,
if it's above ten טפחים, tefachim, כזורק באויר, k'zorek b'avir, it's like
you threw it in the air, meaning you didn't throw it in
the area of רשות הרבים. reshut harabim, למטה מעשרה טפחים, Lematah m'asarah
tefachim, if it's within ten טפחים, tefachim, כזורק בארץ, k'zorek b'aretz, it's
like you threw it on the ground, and הזורק בארץ ארבע אמות
חייב, hazorek b'aretz arba amot chayav, if you throw something four אמות
amot on the ground you are חייב, chayav, so also if it's
within the airspace you are also חייב. chayav. So the גמרא Gemara
says והלא נח, v'ha lo nach, like it says many times, what
do you mean, if you threw it against the wall it rebounded
off of the wall, it didn't come to rest. So אמר רבי
יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan בדבלה שמנה שנינו, bidveilah shmeinah shaninu, a fatty,
juicy, sticky type of a clump of a dates or whatever, so
that sticks against the wall and that's how come it came to
rest. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אמר רבי חייא,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav amar
Rabbi Chiyya, זרק למעלה מעשרה והלכה ונחה בחור כלשהו. zarak l'malah m'asarah
v'halchah v'nachah b'chor kol-she-hu.
You threw something higher than ten טפחים tefachim and now we're not
talking about four אמות amot, in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim we're talking
about,
we're talking about or not only talking about four אמות, amot well
I'll tell you in a minute. You anyway, you threw it and
it went into a little hole in a wall.
But למעלה מעשרה. l'malah m'asarah. We've come to the debate of רבי
מאיר ורבנן. Rabbi Meir v'rabanan. We've come to the debate of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and the rabbis.
רבי מאיר דאמר חוקקין להשלים, Rabbi Meir d'amar chokekin l'hashlim, according to
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says you carve out to make it
full, חייב, chayav, then you have transgressed. ורבנן דאמרי אין חוקקין להשלים,
V'rabanan d'amri ein chokekin l'hashlim, you don't do that, לא מחייב, lo
mechayav, you are not חייב. chayav. What was that, what does that
mean? There's a debate over about a מזוזה mezuzah that let's say
you've got an arch, and because of the arch you don't have
a doorframe that is the doorframe simply, it has to be a
certain width and ten טפחים tefachim high and it has to be
a rectangular width the whole length of the ten טפחים. tefachim. Let's
say towards the top you have an arch and that sort of,
you know, makes the width less through you know at the top
of the height. It needs to be ten טפחים tefachim straight? Yeah,
yeah. So therefore רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says well you imagine it
as if that arch is cut out. If there's like, you know,
if it's an arch that's basically, you know, this, like that.
So in theory you could carve this out, right, and then it
would be a doorframe. Then רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you look
at it as if it is carved out, but the חכמים chachamim
don't say that. So here you threw it higher than ten טפחים
tefachim into a little hole in the wall. It's higher than ten
טפחים tefachim it's not a רשות הרבים, Reshus ha'rabim it's a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid. issue. Okay, you threw it from רשות הרבים Reshus
ha'rabim. onto a wall, where it doesn't go four אמות amos. it
doesn't matter, and it went into a little hole in the wall.
Okay, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says well you imagine it that
you could carve out enough space in that hole that it would
be four טפחים, tefachim, that it'd be four. a four טפחים tefachim
space. So if it's on a wall ten טפחים tefachim high and
you could carve it out, that makes that hole a רשות היחיד.
reshus hayachid, And the rabbis say no you don't do that and
it doesn't make it a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Obviously you could
say there's a big difference between whether we look at this as
a sufficient doorframe for a מזוזה mezuzah and a question whether we
turn something into a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, but the גמרא Gemara.
applies it and says since in theory you could cut it out,
then you would have ten on top of a wall ten טפחים
tefachim high, in theory you could carve out four טפחים tefachim for
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would make it a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid
Okay. תניא נמי הכי ואיצטריכא ליה: Tanya nami hachi ve'itstritcha leih: זרק
למעלה מעשרה, zarak lemalah meiasarah, it
went into a little hole, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir מחייב mechayev וחכמים
vechachamim פוטרים. potrim. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you're חייב, chayav, the
חכמים chachamim say you're פטור. patur. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב:
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: תל המתלקט עשרה מתוך ארבע. tel hamitlakeit
asarah mitoch arba. You have now this is very relevant to the
discussion of islands. You have now a תל, tel, a
like a mound, right, like תל אביב, Tel Aviv, right, תל tel
is a very thing they use all the time in archaeology, תל
tel so and so. Does תל tel mean mound when they say
תל tel like that? Yeah. Okay. So you have a mound that
מתלקט, mitlakeit, which somehow means like goes up in an angle, slopes,
עשרה מתוך ארבע. asarah mitoch arba. It rises up ten טפחים, tefachim,
that's the relevant height for a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid? it rises
up ten טפחים tefachim over a what do you call it, over
a length a base of four אמות. amos So you have four
אמות amos. on the base and as it goes to a ten
טפח tefach height. Okay, there's going to be a simple geometry question.
Okay. So that's the angle. That angle is sharp enough to consider
this slope as if it's a vertical wall. Okay. If it's a
more gradual angle, even though eventually it gets to ten טפחים, tefachim,
you can't call it a wall. Is that sort of clear? Because
you never, right? So if you've got something
very
gradual, right, then you like I don't know, let's say you sort
of went like this, right, and you're over here, you can't say
oh I have a ten טפח tefach wall like this. You don't
have a wall because it is because it's you know, it's a
very gradual slope. But if the slope is significant enough that it
goes up ten within
ארבע אמות, arba amos, within a four אמות. amos Now, it's a
little fun geometry question. Okay, pay attention, Artie. So four אמות amot
is 24 טפחים, tefachim, right, because six טפחים tefachim to an אמה,
amah, so it's ten, this is I'm sorry, this is ten, the
vertical, by 24. And if you want to figure out the angle
here of the slope, okay, so it's opposite over adjacent, tangent. So
tangent x equals 10 over 24. Okay, so it's the arctangent of
10 over 24. I'm impressed you remember. So anyway, these are the
thing this is תורה ומדע. Torah Umadda. This is coming anyway. So
the arctangent of 10 over 24 I did it the other day,
I think it's 26 degrees. You can probably do it right there.
Or something like that. Or maybe
24. Your iPhone should have some app, some kind of.
Anyway, so that angle the ramp is 26 for the Pythagorean theorem.
Oh, okay, right. Because yeah. So anyway, so basically if you have
an angle, whatever that arctangent is, I forget, it's maybe it's 24,
I forget, I figured it out and then I did it on
the calculator and then I anyway, if let's say that whatever that
angle is, 24 degrees, that's important. That means when you have a
that type of an angle, then you have רשות היחיד Reshus ha'yachid
otherwise not. Now when does that come up? It comes up for
islands. Is an island a רשות היחיד? Reshus ha'yachid, If you've got
an island that has a what do you call it, that's got
a seawall, right, if it's a coral reef, then it definitely is
because coral reefs are very straight. But if it's like something like
Manhattan, right, that it sort of slopes, so then the question is
what's that slope?
If that slope is the Manhattan
has a seawall.
It does have a seawall? Okay. There you go. But if that
slope is this degree, this angle or greater, right, then that's considered
a wall. If it's not, then it's not considered a wall. So
this is a very relevant for discussions of like is Manhattan an
island for all of these questions relating to עירובין eruvin in Manhattan
and so on. Yes.
That would make it easy to build an עירוב eruv in to
create an עירוב eruv on most islands or to build an עירוב
eruv in a hilly area. Yes. Because that's not a very steep
slope.
Right. I mean any area that has real like mountains or hills
or whatever, that I mean that is a 22, 24 degrees is
a pretty gradual slope.
Yeah, I've been to צפת, Safed, you wouldn't need any. Right.
Now there is a question which I'll address which the רמב"ן Ramban
discusses as well. About which is at what stage if the מחיצות
Mechitzos are completely non-experienced, is the guy still have to be near
it like you're עומד בתוך המחיצות, Omed b'toch ha'mechitzot, but somebody could
say what's no different than now with the fake, you know, walls
of the צורת הפתח, Tzuras ha'pesach, we also don't experience the walls.
Anyway, that this would be better than a צורה. Tzura.
Right, right, this is a real wall if it has that angle.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, תניא נמי
הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly. I'm sorry, so תל המתלקט
עשרה מתוך ארבע, Tel ha'mitlaket asara mitoch arba, so here it's talking
about it for חיוב, Chiyuv, not to make it a רשות היחיד
Reshus ha'yachid, for carrying, but for saying you're חייב. Chayav. So if
you had that it went up עשרה טפחים Asara tefachim within ארבע
אמות, Arba amos, so the top of it now is those are
walls, the top is a רשות היחיד, Reshus ha'yachid. וזרק ונח על
גביו, V'zarak v'nach al gabav, and you threw from רשות הרבים Reshus
ha'rabim. and it landed on it, חייב, Chayav, because it is a
רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid that counts as a wall. תניא נמי הכי,
Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, and here it's using it more
לקולא L'kula for עירוב Eruv purposes, like we would, like I had
discussed. מבוי ששוה לתוכו Mavoi she'shaveh l'tocho ונעשה מדרון לרשות הרבים, V'na'aseh
madron l'reshus ha'rabim, so you have your מבוי, Mavoi, you have your
courtyard, okay, here's your courtyard. Now, your courtyard has three walls around
it, and out here is the רשות הרבים. Reshus ha'rabim Can you
carry in your courtyard? What well what you have to do is
you have to do something symbolic for the fourth wall. You either
have to do, you know, a לחי, Lechi, like a vertical post,
or a קורה, Koroh, a horizontal post, for your fourth wall to
let you carry in your courtyard. But let's say you didn't do
that, but what actually happened was that if there's a slope going
from your courtyard into the רשות הרבים. Reshus ha'rabim. The רשות הרבים
Reshus ha'rabim, is down here, and there's this slope, or maybe a
slope the other way, okay, but let's say it's like this, there's
this slope. So you don't need to do something for your fourth
wall. That slope, if it's a good enough angle, counts as the
wall as your fourth wall. Okay, so מבוי ששוה לתוכו, Mavoi she'shaveh
l'tocho, it's flat on the inside, ונעשה מדרון לרשות הרבים, V'na'aseh madron
l'reshus ha'rabim, and it slopes down to the רשות הרבים. Reshus ha'rabim
או ששוה לרשות הרבים ונעשה מדרון לתוכו, O she'shaveh l'reshus ha'rabim v'na'aseh
madron l'tocho,
or it's level to the רשות הרבים, Reshus ha'rabim, here's the רשות
הרבים reshut harabim. is this brown book, right, and this is your
מבוי, Mavoi, and they're on the same level, but after you start
entering the מבוי, Mavoi, there's a big slope down to the rest
of the מבוי. Mavoi. So again, that sloping part counts as a
wall. In those cases, אותו מבוי אינו צריך לא ללחי ולא לקורה,
Oso mavoi eino tzarich lo l'lechi v'lo l'koroh, you do not need
either a post or a beam, because it is a wall. רבי
חייא בר רבי חנינא בן גמליאל אומר, Rabbi Chiyya bar Rabbi Chanina
ben Gamliel omer, תל המתלקט עשרה מתוך ארבע Tel ha'mitlaket asara mitoch
arba וזרק ונח על גביו חייב, V'zarak v'nach al gabav chayav, same
point that only in the parameters when it's got enough of a
slope, it goes up עשרה Asara within ארבע אמות, Arba amos, then
it counts as a wall, then the top is a רשות היחיד.
reshut hayachid Okay, so everybody can do that as a homework assignment,
it's arctan ten over twenty-four. Okay, now משנה. Mishna. זרק לתוך ארבע
אמות ונתגלגל חוץ לארבע אמות, Zarak l'toch arba amos v'nisgalgel chutz l'arba
amos, you threw something within ארבע אמות Arba amos and then it
rolled out, okay, פטור, Patur, you're exempt. That's pretty obvious because certainly
if you weren't intending to do it, we've had before you intended
to do four and it went eight, you're exempt. Okay, but this
might mean even if you were intending to do it, you were
intending for it to land and roll, maybe you're exempt. Well, why?
We'll see. חוץ לארבע אמות ונתגלגל לתוך ארבע אמות, Chutz l'arba amos
v'nisgalgel l'toch arba amos, if you threw it outside and it hit
the ground and it rolled back, you're חייב. Chayav. So presumably the
reason for this is when it hits the ground, it's considered coming
to rest. So if you threw it and it hit the ground
in four amos and then rolled out, well, first it came to
rest within ארבע אמות, Arba amos, and the next movement was a
separate thing, it wasn't your act, or it was less than four
amos, whatever it was, you're exempt because that was not, because it
had the hitting the ground was a stopping point. Similarly, you threw
it out of four amos, okay, and it hit the ground, then
you're already חייב. Chayav. The fact that afterwards it rolled back, that
does not exempt you. So the basic well yeah so the basic
assumption of the משנה Mishna is that when it hits the ground,
it's considered that it stopped. But that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara
questions, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara So the
גמרא Gemara says והא לא נח? V'ha lo nach? But it didn't
come to rest. It hit the ground and kept on moving. Okay,
now you might remember before that there was an opinion that everybody
about this right when you threw it through רשות הרבים, reshut harabim,
that there was an opinion that if it was within שלשה טפחים,
Shelosha tefachim, everybody would say you're חייב. Chayav. Within שלשה טפחים, Shelosha
tefachim, it's like on the ground. So presumably that means even rolling
on the ground you're חייב. Chayav. So תוספות Tosafot points out that
this גמרא Gemara is not assuming that. If you assume that, the
whole thing is obvious. If even flying through the air within שלשה
טפחים, Shelosha tefachim, it doesn't need to come to rest, certainly hitting
the ground is sufficient in terms of coming to rest. But this
גמרא Gemara is not assuming that, assuming that it really has to
rest in a very stable, stopped way. So it's got the problem,
even if it hit the ground and it rolled back, it didn't
come to rest. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan,
it's sort of like the גמרא Gemara before about the water, right,
that even the moving around on the water is not enough. This
גמרא Gemara assumes you need much more in terms of coming to
rest. So אמר רבי יוחנן והוא שנח על גבי משהו, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan v'hu she'nach al gabei mashehu, okay, we're saying that it did
come to rest for a moment, it hit the ground, it sort
of, you know, was sort of stopped for a moment then. and
then started rolling back. So that's what he says. Now we're going
to get even more radical than anyway, something that even, whatever, you'll
see.
Something that aren't you meaning like a stone? a כלי?
or yeah, a rock,
some rocky part of the ground?
Yeah, but something caused it to stop. You threw it, it hit
a rock, it fell behind a rock and therefore the rock stopped
its movement for a minute and then it sort of its momentum
carried it around the rock and it continued to move. Something like
that.
Since we were saying before that the ground isn't considered הנחה, so
you're saying that the...
No, no, no. It's not that the ground isn't, it's that it's
moving. Obviously the ground is הנחה. It's not the question of what
is it on. You're right, the language is a little distracting because
the language says sounds like it's question it's not on the ground,
it's on a
thing, okay? But the... okay, so but yeah the... but I think
it's easier to understand that it means like a little thing stopped
its movement for a moment and then it continued. Okay, now but
we're going to take a look, let's see we go further. תניא
נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught something similarly. זרק חוץ לארבע
אמות ודחפתה הרוח. Zarak chutz l'arba amot v'dachafta haruach. You threw it
outside of four אמות amot. and then the wind blew it back
והכניסתו v'hichnisato and brought it within your, you know, back to its
original location. אף על פי שחזרה והוציאתו, Af al pi shechazra v'hotziato,
even then the wind went out and went in the other direction
and took it back out. So it like blew it back to
you and then blew it away from you. In all those cases
פטור, patur, you are exempt.
Because it didn't come to, because it didn't stop outside of your
four אמות. amot It came back, so therefore you're certainly פטור patur
when it blew it back to you because it was a continuous
movement. Now the question is why aren't you חייב chayav when then
it continues to blow it out in another direction? So presumably that
wasn't your intent so that you're exempt for. Okay.
Now but there's not a case where like it stopped?
It didn't stop. It was a fluid type of a movement. That
stopping is the next point. אחזתה הרוח משהו, Achazata haruach mashehu, if
the wind causes it to stop for a moment. Like the wind
causes it to spin around in mid-air and causes it to to
stop in flight. אף על פי שחזרה והכניסתו חייב, Af al pi
shechazra v'hichnisato chayav, even though it brought it back to you you
are חייב. chayav. So here you see that even hovering in air
by the wind, as long as it's stable for a moment, you're
חייב. chayav. Now again, I would like somebody to explain to me
why hovering in air because of the wind is considered more stable
than floating on a pond. Okay, I don't exactly get it. Maybe
for that one second but the wind is holding it it's stable.
But you know what? Something floating on a pond could also based
on how windy it is or whatever be stable for one second.
So I really don't get, תוספות Tosafot tries to bring all these
discussions together. It is not clear to me how they're all consistent.
Anyway, but that's the point, okay? So flying through the air, no;
within three טפחים, tefachim, no; but momentarily paused because it hit a
rock or because the wind held it, that would be yes, that
would be considered a הנחה. אמר רבא, Rava said רבא. Rava תוך
ג' לרבנן צריך הנחה על גבי משהו. Toch gimel l'Rabbanan tzarich hanacha
al gabei mashehu. And here we are exactly saying that, that explicitly
opposite of what we said before. The Rabbis who argue on רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, remember רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said it could be
flying through mid-air you're חייב. chayav. So there was an opinion before
that if it was within three טפחים, tefachim, even the Rabbis agree
that you're חייב chayav because that is like it's on the ground.
Here רבא Rava is saying no, here in this גמרא Gemara is
assuming that rolling on the ground is actually going to be פטור,
patur, that actually has to physically come to rest. So that's what
he's saying. Even within three טפחים, tefachim, my God, even on the
ground itself, the Rabbis would say צריך הנחה על גבי משהו, tzarich
hanacha al gabei mashehu, they argue on רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
they would say even within three טפחים, tefachim, even on the ground,
it has to stop. It can't just continuously be rolling.
יתיב מריימר וקאמר לה להא שמעתא, Yativ Mareimar v'ka-amar lah l'ha shemata,
so מריימר Mareimar was sitting down and telling over this discussion and
this position of רבא. Rava אמר ליה רבינא למריימר, Amar lei Ravina
l'Mareimar, so רבינא Ravina said to מריימר, Mareimar, לאו היינו מתניתין? lav
hainu matnitin? One minute, that's our משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה Mishnah says
that it, you know, that it sort of stopped and rolled back
to you. ואמר
רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rabbi Yochanan, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says והוא
שנח על גבי משהו. vehu shenach al gabei mashehu.
So and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that that's only when it
stopped on something, meaning why did, obviously what רבא Rava. said is
implicit in what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. Our question was in
the משנה, Mishnah, oh, why is it considered to have stopped? and
we made a we made a special case that it bumped into
a rock or something. So why it would there should have been
an easier answer. This is what I told you when we began
learning this. The easy answer should have been it's within three טפחים
tefachim of the ground. Within three טפחים tefachim of the ground, we
said a few days ago, counts as if it's on the ground.
We didn't say that. So you see that we are assuming that
being on the ground or being within three טפחים tefachim on the
ground does not does not suffice. That actually has to physically stop.
Okay? Is that clear? Meaning nobody's debating it. We're just saying, yeah,
we just been saying that. רבא says you know what? Even within
three טפחים tefachim on the ground it has to stop. So the
גמרא Gemara says, yeah, we've just been saying that because we've just
been saying that this thing that fell and bounced and whatever had
to actually stop and it's not enough that it's within three טפחים
tefachim of the ground. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה, amar
lei, so he said back to him,
מתגלגל קאמרת? mitgalgel ka'amrat? You're talking about rolling. rolling? מגלגל אין סופו
לנוח. misgalgel ein sofo lanuach. That case where it's rolling and bouncing
and moving, that's obvious that it needs to actually stop even if
it's on the ground or within three טפחים. tefachim. רבא, what רבא
was saying was not so obvious. אבל האי, Aval hai, in רבא'ס
Rava's case, כיון דסופו לנוח, keivan desofo lanuach, since it will come
to a rest, אף על גב דלא נח, af al gav delo
nach, כמאן דמחת דמי. keman demachat dami. I might think that even
before it came to a rest, קמשמע לן kamashma lan not. Now
what is the scenario? So think like this. You've got something, by
the way, this is all very relevant also to questions of like
pushing a baby carriage, something that is touching the ground, how much
does it have to actually stop to be considered to come to
a rest? Okay, so before just remind you, the גמרא Gemara said
within three טפחים, tefachim, certainly rolling on the ground within three טפחים,
tefachim, it's like it came to rest, it doesn't have to stop.
Here the גמרא'ס Gemara's saying no. Within three טפחים tefachim no, even
on the ground no. How about the thing you throw and threw
and rolled back? That would only be that it first let's say
bumped into a rock and then moved around it and that's because
it came to actually rest, but otherwise no. So the גמרא Gemara.
says so what's רבא telling us that's new? We've saying that, that
the thing rolling has to stop, you know, what's new about what
רבא'ס Rava's saying? So the גמרא'ס Gemara's saying no. That case where
you're throwing it and it's rolling and it's rolling this way or
it's rolling back, that's a case obviously it's not considered to come
to rest unless it stops prominent. רבא is a case where it's
about to come to rest. What would רבא'ס Rava's case be? Let's
say you're throwing it and it's within three טפחים tefachim and it's
about to hit the ground. Okay? So that's a case where it's
in the process of actually stabilizing and coming to rest in a
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim There we might, let's say it won't roll,
okay, and you threw your knapsack, okay, it's gonna hit the ground.
So there we might say and especially רש"י Rashi says let's say
even threw it from here and it's going down like this. So
it's heading straight to rest. There you might say once it's within
three טפחים tefachim and it's going to rest as soon as it
hits the ground, it's like it already hit the ground. Okay, so
רבא says no, it has not come to rest until it actually
lands on the ground. What difference does it make? Either way you're
חייב. chayav. Okay, so the difference רש"י Rashi would say, wow, special
case of a קרבן, korban, let's say you remembered before it hit
the ground what you had done. So because you remembered before the
מלאכה melacha was done, you don't bring a קרבן. korban. Or you
could say let's say it was coming to rest, but it was
coming sort of like at an angle or something like this and
it was going to rest less than ארבע טפחים, arba tefachim, but
when it was within... less than ארבע אמות, arba amot, but when
it was within three טפחים, tefachim, it was still outside of ארבע
אמות. arba amot. So you could have scenarios where it's important to
say even when it's coming to a rest, it has to literally
hit the ground and stop. So this גמרא Gemara is different than
גמרות Gemaras before. גמרות Gemaras before we had flying through midair and
three טפחים tefachim and this and that. This גמרא Gemara from the
beginning to the end here is really coming to rest. I don't
care if it's within three טפחים, tefachim, I don't care if it's
hit the ground, even if it's on a pond, it has not
come to rest, it really has to stop and that's been the
consistent thrust in all of this גמרא. Gemara,
Certainly you don't say קלוט כמי שהונחה. kalut kemi shehunachah. Okay. So
we're covering a lot of ground. Moving on, next משנה. Mishnah. הזורק
בים ארבע אמות פטור. Hazorek beyam arba amot patur. If you threw
something into an ocean, ארבע אמות, arba amot, an ocean is not
a רשות הרבים, reshut harabim although boats go through the ocean, it's
considered a כרמלית, karmelit, so you're exempt. אם היה רקק מים, Im
hayah rekak mayim, now let's say however you had a puddle of
water, ורשות הרבים מהלכת בו, v'reshut harabim mehelechet bo, and that was
within the middle of the thoroughfare, right, so people would walk through
the puddle, so הזורק לתוכו ארבע אמות חייב. hazorek letocho arba amot
chayav. If you throw ארבע אמות arba amot in the puddle, it's
a big puddle let's say, you're חייב, chayav, because the puddle is
a רשות הרבים reshut harabim. if it's actually not an ocean where
ships go, but it's on the ground and people walk through it,
that makes it a... okay, so we'll talk about that. וכמה הוא
רקק מים? Ve'chamah hu rekak mayim? What,
what type of a puddle would still be considered part of the
רשות הרבים reshut harabim, if people walk through it? פחות מעשרה טפחים.
Pachot me'asarah tefachim. Only less than ten טפחים. tefachim. Once it's עשרה
טפחים asarah tefachim deep, then it's a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. or
certainly it's not part of the
רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. רקק מים ברשות הרבים ומהלכת בו. Rekak mayim
b'reshut harabim u'mehelechet bo. Now it says, repeats itself, a puddle of
water and the thoroughfare is going through it, הזורק בתוכו ארבע אמות
חייב. hazorek betocho arba amot chayav. If you throw four אמות you're
חייב. chayav. Mamash the exact same thing we just said. So the
גמרא Gemara says why you repeating yourself? אמר ליה המנונא לרבא. Amar
lei Hamnuna l'Rava. So one of the rabbis said to רבא. בשלמא
הילוך תרי זימני. Bishlama hiluch terei zimnei. I understand why it had
to repeat this. If you have a public thoroughfare going through a
puddle,
you're חייב. chayav. So you had to say twice if people are
מהלכת בו, mehelechet bo, that the thoroughfare is going through it. הא
קמשמע לן, Ha kamashma lan, that's teaching us הילוך על ידי הדחק
שמיה הילוך. hiluch al yedei hadechak shemei hiluch. It says it a
second time to insist, I really mean it, even if you're going
through a puddle, which somehow means that even if it's not so
convenient to go through a puddle, even if it's על ידי הדחק,
al yedei hadechak, people go when it's like because they have no
other choice, that still counts and it's not a nice way of
walking through a רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, that still makes it part
of the רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. הא קמשמע לן הילוך על ידי
הדחק שמיה הילוך. Ha kamashma lan hiluch al yedei hadechak shemei hiluch.
But הילוך שמיה הילוך, hiluch shemei hiluch, תשמיש על ידי הדחק לאו
שמיה תשמיש. tashmish al yedei hadechak lav shemei tashmish. The other thing
it also tells us is just only מהלכת בו, mehelechet bo, only
if they're walking through it. What if they're using it without walking
through it? Right, remember we discussed before if you have like a
platform in רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim. if it's nine טפחים tefachim high...
and easy to use, it's part of the רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim.
If it's lower than nine טפחים tefachim and hard to use, it's
not part of the רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim Why? That was a
principle of תשמיש על ידי הדחק לאו שמי תשמיש. tashmish al yedey
had'chak lav shmei tashmish.
Using something, even if you're occasionally using it, but it's without, it's
not a convenient use, it's not considered really a good use and
it doesn't incorporate into the רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. So this is
saying only מהלכת בו. mehalechet bo. It says מהלכת מהלכת mehalechet mehalechet
two times to say only this is considered part of the רשות
הרבים Reshut HaRabim. because people can walk through it. So even though
it's difficult, if it's actually walked through, that makes it part of
רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim
But if it's—right, yeah, but if it's used and it's only used
with difficulty, then that is not enough to make it part of
רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. So only הילוך, hiluch, not תשמיש. tashmish. Then
it goes on. Okay, that I get, why it had to emphasize
הילוך. hiluch. אלא רקק רקק תרי זימני למה לי? ela rakak rakak
trei zimni lama li? Why'd it have to say twice, repeat the
scenario, if you got a puddle you got a puddle? It does
say twice מהלכת בו mehalechet bo to emphasize only walking, not other
usages. Why repeat the scenario of the puddle?
So the גמרא Gemara. says חד בימות החמה וחד בימות הגשמים, chad
bimot hachama vechad bimot hageshamim, to tell me that it doesn't matter
whether we're talking about the summer or the rainy season, the winter.
צריכא, tsricha, and it needs to tell me both scenarios. דאי תנא
חדא, de'i tana chada, had it just told me one time a
puddle, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would've said הני מילי בימות החמה,
hani mili bimot hachama,
when is a puddle part of the רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim during
the summer? Okay, why? דעבידי אינשי דמסקלי לאקרורי נפשייהו, de'avidi inshi demaskeli
l'akruri nafshaihu, people like walking through a puddle, it gets them, it
cools them off. We're like all seven-year-old kids, so we like walking
through the puddle. אבל בימות הגשמים, aval bimot hageshamim, in the rainy
season, לא, lo, who wants to walk through a puddle? It's wet
enough as it is. So maybe I would say you don't use
it so much, not enough to make it a רשות הרבים. Reshut
HaRabim. ואי אשמעינן בימות הגשמים, ve'i ashmeinan bimot hageshamim, if it said
that it was, it was part of the רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim.
in the rainy season, why? דכיון דמטנפי, dekivan demitanfai, since anyway your
clothes are muddy and dirty, right? You can't keep your clothes too
clean during the rainy season. So, and, so לא אכפת ליה, lo
ichpat leh, so what do I care? I'm already wet and muddy,
I'll walk through the puddle. אבל בימות החמה, aval bimot hachama, in
the summer, לא, lo, I might've thought that then it's not part
of the רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim So it had to tell me
whether summer or whether twice, it doesn't matter what time of year,
people will use it enough that it's considered part of the רשות
הרבים. Reshut HaRabim אביי אמר צריכא, Abaye amar tsricha, Abaye says another
way.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka d'atach amina,
I would've thought הני מילי
היכא דלא הוי ארבע אמות, hani mili heicha d'lo havi arba amot,
that maybe it's only part of the רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim. if
it's not four amot. Why? אבל היכא דהוי ארבע אמות, aval heicha
d'havi arba amot, if it's four amot wide, who wants to walk
through a puddle that wide? Once it gets big enough, אקופי מקפי
ליה, akufi makpai leh, you're going to walk around it. So therefore
it had to tell me not only it doesn't matter what season,
it doesn't matter even how wide it is. רב אשי אמר צריכא,
Rav Ashi amar tsricha, no you need to tell me the opposite,
not even if it's very wide, but even if it's narrow. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, salka d'atach amina, I might've thought הני מילי היכא דהוי
ארבע, hani mili heicha d'havi arba, when is it considered part of
the רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim. when it is wide, when it's four
and more. אבל היכא דלא הוי ארבע, aval heicha d'lo havi arba,
if it's not four, if it's not four,
then I would say, I would say מיפסי פסי ליה, mifsi pasi
leh, maybe you would just step over it. You wouldn't actually walk
through it. So if you'd step over it, that's not enough to
make it part of רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. Now of course, yeah,
but here it actually says, I don't know because, you know, the,
what do you call it? Sometimes the גמרא, Gemara whatever, the editor
here, the publisher, doesn't always do the grammar right because here it
has ארבעה arbaa with the ה hei which is ארבעה טפחים, arbaa
tefachim, although Abaye was explicit about ארבע אמות. arba amot. So I
don't know if, I have to check the גרסאות. girsaot. Presumably he's
talking about the same scenario of Abaye and going in the reverse,
not shifting to four tefachim. Okay, but anyway, I would've thought that
if it's small enough you would jump over it and therefore I
would say it's not part of רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. And it
tells me no, even if it's very narrow, it's still part of
רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. ואזדא רב אשי לטעמיה, ve'azda Rav Ashi l'taameh,
Rav Ashi goes according to his reasoning. דאמר רב אשי, damar Rav
Ashi, Rav Ashi said האי מן דזרק ונח אגודא דגמלא, hai man
d'zarak v'nach aguda d'gamla, if you threw something and it landed on,
let's say, a beam on a bridge, but the beam was like
out of place, it was sitting on top of the bridge, it
wasn't part of the actual floor of the bridge. מחייב, mechayiv, you're
chayiv. Why? שהרי רבים בוקעים בו, sheharei rabim bokim bo, people will
walk over it. They don't necessarily jump over it, even if it's
a little puddle, even if it's a little beam, you'll still walk
through it. And since you walk through it, that makes it part
of רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim So it doesn't matter, what? גמלא Gamla
is a bridge? Yeah. Anyway, so it doesn't matter what season it
is, it doesn't matter how wide or how narrow it is, as
long as it is regularly, you know, used enough by the רבים,
rabim, whatever enough is, that makes it part of the רשות הרבים.
reshut harabbim. Yes, Charlie.
What, class long jumpers can easily jump four handbreadths?
Good to know, yeah.
What do I understand, what does your English say, by the way,
by Rav Ashi? Does it say four tefachim or four amot? Four
handbreadths. Four handbreadths. So assuming the ארבעה arbaa is correct and that
it's different than Abaye who was talking about
ארבע
אמות.
arba
amot.
Yeah, that's what I thought before. The whole רשות הרבים reshut harabbim
is flooded, the whole thing? Yeah, and it's like a big flood,
and it's not
mud. I understand. It's a good question. It's a good question. Right?
I mean look we said before that רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. changes
its identity, but again the question is how permanent was that change
and so on.
Yes, whether the briefness of time has any relevance. Now it's not
possible.
Right, presumably that is correct.
But it might, right, so I'm saying like there's St. Marks, right?
Like you know people wanted to get through it because like you
know it's a major thing even
like swimming it because it was kind of fun.
Yeah, but the ten טפחים tefachim seems to just be defining it
as a different location. It doesn't matter and therefore it's a different
location and it doesn't get incorporated. No, the ten טפחים tefachim deep
does not seem to be a use consideration. It seems to be
a more formal issue that it's a different location and therefore it
doesn't get incorporated into the רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
Okay, this הוה אמינא hava amina of winter-summer, yes, is this the
first time that we've seen
the same space, the same definition, but it's subjective now because of
how it's used?
Right. Well the גמרא before, for example, talking about similar things, talking
about if you remember, dung piles and thorn bushes on the edge
of רשות הרבים reshut harabbim, and how much do people actually, are
they willing to trample on it or do they go around it?
So again, I mean, did we say that like in one place
people
would...
right, so you don't mean as much subjective as you mean sort
of contextual, right, you know? So, right, so that's interesting in terms
of definition of רשויות. reshuyot. I mean we had obviously things about
how do people carry things in certain ways in certain places, but
in terms of like basic, you know, architecture types of issues of
רשויות, reshuyot,
right, less so, less so. Yeah, I'd have to think if there
are any other parallels. All right, let's start the next one. הזורק
מן הים ליבשה, Hazorek min hayam leyabasha, so here we go, that
you're actually on a ship or you throw from the ocean into
the dry land, ומן היבשה לים, u'min hayabasha layam, or from the
dry land. We're assuming the dry land is a רשות הרבים. reshut
harabbim So we had just implicitly said before
that the ocean was not a רשות הרבים, reshut harabim. now we're
also saying it's not a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. The ocean is
a כרמלית. karmelit. ומן הים לספינה ומן הספינה לים, U'min hayam lesfina
u'min hasfina layam, or similarly from the ocean to a boat or
from the boat to the ocean, ומן הספינה לחברתה, u'min hasfina lechavertah,
from one boat to its neighboring boat, in all those cases פטור,
patur, you're exempt. In the first set of cases you're exempt because
it's
from a כרמלית, karmelit, which is the ocean, to either רשות הרבים
reshut harabim or רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid? From one boat to the
next boat, the boats are רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Why is the
boat רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid Because it's got the walls of the
boat, right, those are, and it's ten טפחים tefachim high, so the
boat is a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid, So one boat to another
boat, of course you're exempt because that's one רשות reshut to another
רשות. reshut. Even though it's passing over a כרמלית, karmelit, over the
ocean. One minute. ספינות קשורות זו בזו, Sfinot kshurot zu be-zu, if
the boats are tied one to another, then like maybe you'll have
it... then docked, well or maybe you'll have it like a chain.
מטלטלים מזו לזו, Metaltelin mi-zu le-zu, you can carry from one to
the next. You're allowed even לכתחילה. lechatchila. אם אינם קשורות, Im enam
kshurot, if they're not tied, אף על פי שמוקפות, af al pi
she'mukafot, even if they're like touching one another, sort of next to
one another, אין מטלטלין מזו לזו, ein metaltelin mi-zu le-zu, you cannot.
Why? Even though it's one רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. to another רשות
היחיד, reshut hayachid again it gets into like these עירוב eiruv issues
about if they're owned by different people then you cannot go from
one private domain to another unless you've come together in the box
of matzot, in the עירוב, eiruv, and that's really what this second
point is about. Let's take a little look at the גמרא. איתמר,
Itmar, it was taught.
ספינה, Sfina, you've got your boat and you want to draw water
from the ocean, okay, and you're on your boat and it's שבת.
So the ocean is a כרמלית, karmelit, your boat is a רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid, How are you able to draw water? It's rabbinically
forbidden, not biblically. How are you able to draw water? רב הונא
אמר מוציא ממנה זיז כלשהו וממלא. Rav Huna amar motzi mimena ziz
kol-shehu u'memaleh. You have a little platform sticking out of the boat,
a little protrusion, and then you draw water. What does that do?
We'll see in a minute.
From under the platform you draw water?
Here's your boat, right, here's the ocean is all around, you stuck
a little platform here, this is the side of the boat, here,
your deck is here, okay, and the ocean is here. You stick
a little protrusion out and you're standing on the deck and you
lower your bucket and you draw the water. So what does that
little protrusion do? We'll find out in a minute.
Okay. רב הונא אמר מוציא ממנה זיז כלשהו וממלא. Rav Huna amar
motzi mimena ziz kol-shehu u'memaleh. כסבר, Kasavar, I'm sorry, I said it,
רב הונא אמר עושה מקום ארבעה וממלא. Rav Huna amar oseh makom
arbaah u'memaleh. No, you have to make a space of four טפחים.
tefachim. So what רש״י Rashi says that means is, not just a
space, what רש״י Rashi says it means is you build here on
the wall of the boat, you build here like a little box
with a, you know, with like the bottom, no wall on the
bottom, no floor on the bottom. So this little box has walls
עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, so it's like a little רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid, with no floor, but it's a little רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid.
and you lower your bucket down so the walls are considered to
go straight down, so they make the ocean directly underneath it a
רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, so you can lower your bucket and draw
the water and it's all being drawn within a רשות היחיד. reshut
hayachid. Now normally we would never say that... walls suspended up there
if the bottom make the bottom space רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid but
this is something that we do say in the case of an
ocean. So those are the two opinions. Okay now the גמרא explains
why they have different דעות. de'ayas. רב הונא אמר אם מוציא מן
הזיז כל שהוא Rav Huna amar im motzi min hazees kol shehoo
or protrusion is enough וממלא u'mimalei קסבר כרמלית מארעא משחינן. kasavar karmelis
me'ara mashchina. He says where the air space of a כרמלית karmelis
is like the air space of a רשות הרבים. When does it
end, when does the air space of a רשות הרבים end?
After ten טפחים. tefachim. So now you have an ocean, where do
you start counting your ten טפחים tefachim from? From the ocean floor
or from the water level? So he says that קסבר כרמלית מארעא
משחינן kasavar karmelis me'ara mashchina and you count starting from the ocean
floor. ואויר מקום פטור va'avir makom patur and anything higher than ten
טפחים tefachim is מקום פטור. makom patur. So most of the water
is in a מקום פטור, makom patur, isn't even in the כרמלית,
karmelis, right? Because it's only the floor and the first ten טפחים
tefachim of water is the כרמלית. karmelis. Anything higher is מקום פטור
makom patur and you're allowed to take from a מקום פטור makom
patur to רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid.
So why do you need the זיז zeez then?
We'll see. ובדין הוא, u'vidin hu, thank you, ואויר מקום פטור דזיז
נמי לא ליבעי. va'avir makom patur dezees nami lo libay. Really you
shouldn't even need the זיז. zeez. Okay. אלא כי היכי דליהוי
ליה היכרא ela ki haychi d'lahavei lei hikera but just that it
should be a little sign for you or a little remembrance, you
shouldn't come to confuse this with a normal כרמלית. karmelis. A normal
כרמלית karmelis you wouldn't be able to do it לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Here,
so you remember that this is different because when you make this
protrusion that somehow is a little ring like a little string around
your finger, you remember that this is a special case because the
water is above is in a מקום פטור makom patur is above
the floor of the כרמלית. karmelis. רב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא
אמרי Rav Chisda v'Rabba bar Rav Huna amri but רב חסדא Rav
Chisda and רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna say עושה
מקום ארבעה osa makom arba'a you need this little booth of four
וממלא u'mimalei קסבר כרמלית משפת מים משחינן. kasavar karmelis misfas mayim mashchina.
No, we count the ocean, we count the ten טפחים tefachim starting
from the water level. מיא ארעא סמיכתא maya ara smichta it's like
one it's like thick dirt with the ocean floor. So the ocean
floor and the water is all like the ground, it's all thick
dirt as it were. And you start counting from the top of
the water. אי לא עביד מקום ארבעה ee lo avidei makom arba'a
if you would not have made this booth of four
טפחים tefachim קא מטלטל מכרמלית לרשות היחיד ka metaltel me'karmelis l'reshut hayachid
you would be carrying from the כרמלית karmelis to רשות היחיד because
the top the water you're getting is actually coming from a כרמלית.
karmelis. So the only way you make it acceptable is you make
a little booth and it's as if the walls go straight down
and then you're taking from within a רשות היחיד.
About ten טפחים tefachim high?
Yes. And the special thing we say by the ocean. So we
will see more about this on שבת.